Chapter 53.
the gam.
The ostensible reason why Ahab did not go on board of the wher we had spoken
was this. The wind and sea be token storms. But even had this not been the
case, he would not, after all perhaps have boarded her, judging by his
subsequent conduct on similar occasions, if so it had been that by the process of
hailing, he had obtained a negative answer to the question he put. For, as
it eventually turned out, he cared not to consort, even for five minutes, with
any stranger captain, except he could contribute some of that information he
so absorbingly sought. But all this might remain inadequately estimated,
were not something said here of the peculiar usages of whailing vessels when
meeting each other in foreign seas, and especially on a common cruising ground.
If two strangers crossing the pine baronss in New York State, or the
equally desolate Salisbury plain in England, if casually encountering each
other in such inhospitable wilds, these twain, for the life of them, cannot well
avoid a mutual salutation, and stopping for a moment to interchange the news,
and perhaps sitting down for a while, and resting in concert, then how much
more natural that upon the illimitable pinebear s and Salisbury plains of the
sea. Two whailing vessels describing each other at the ends of the earth off
Lone Fanning's Island or the far away King's Mills. How much more natural I
say that under such circumstances these ships should not only interchange hails,
but come into still closer, more friendly, and sociable contact. And
especially would this seem to be a matter of course in the case of vessels
owned in one seapport and whose captains, officers, and not a few of the
men are personally known to each other, and consequently have all sorts of dear
domestic things to talk about. For the long absent ship, the outwardbounder
perhaps has letters on board. At any rate, she will be sure to let her have
some papers of a date a year or two later than the last one on her blurred
and thumbworn files. And in return for that courtesy, the outwardbound ship
would receive the latest whailing intelligence from the cruising ground to
which she may be destined, a thing of the utmost importance to her. And in
degree all of this will hold true concerning whailing vessels crossing
each other's track on the cruising ground itself, even though they are
equally long absent from home. For one of them may have received a transfer of
letters from some third and now far remote vessel, and some of those letters
may be for the people of the ship she now meets. Besides, they would exchange
the wailing news and have an agreeable chat, for not only would they meet with
all these sympathies of sailors, but likewise with all the peculiar
congenialities arising from a common pursuit and mutually shared privations and perils.
Nor would difference of country make any very essential difference, that is, so
long as both parties speak one language, as is the case with Americans and
English. Though to be sure, from the small number of English whalers, such
meetings do not very often occur, and when they do occur, there is too apt to
be a sort of shyness between them. For your Englishman is rather reserved, and
your Yankee, he does not fancy that sort of thing in anybody but himself.
Besides, the English whalers sometimes affect a kind of metropolitan
superiority over the American whalers, regarding the long lean Nantucketer with
his nondescript provincialisms as a sort of sea peasant. But where this
superiority in the English whaleman does really consist, it would be hard to say,
seeing that the Yankees in one day collectively kill more whales than all
the English collectively in 10 years.
But this is a harmless little foil in the English whale hunters which the
Nantucketer does not take much to heart, probably because he knows he has a few
foibless himself.
So then we see that of all ships separately sailing the sea, the whalers
have most reason to be sociable, and they are so. Whereas some merchant ships
crossing each other's wake in the Mid-Atlantic will oftenimes pass on
without so much as a single word of recognition, mutually cutting each other
on the high seas like a brace of dandies in Broadway, and all the time indulging
perhaps in finical criticism upon each other's rig. As for men of war, when
they chance to meet at sea, they first go through such a string of silly
bowings and scrapings, such a ducking of ensons, that there does not seem to be
much right down hardy goodwill and brotherly love about it at all. As
touching slave ships meeting, why they are in such a predigious hurry, they run
away from each other as soon as possible. And as for pirates, when they
chance to cross each other's crossbones, the first hail is, "How many skulls?"
The same way that whalers hail, "How many barrels?" And that question once
answered, pirates straight away steer apart, for they are infernal villains on
both sides, and don't like to see over much of each other's villainous likenesses.
But look at the godly, honest, unostentious, hospitable, sociable,
free, and easy whaler. What does the whaler do when she meets another whaler
in any sort of decent weather? She has a gam, a thing so utterly unknown to all
other ships that they never heard of the name even. And if by chance they should
hear of it, they only grin at it and repeat gamesome stuff about spouters and
blubber boilers and such like pretty exclamations.
Why it is that all merchant seammen and also all pirates and man of wars men and
slave ship sailors cherish such a scornful feeling towards whale ships.
This is a question it would be hard to answer because in the case of pirates
say I should like to know whether that profession of theirs has any particular
glory about it. It sometimes ends in uncommon elevation indeed but only at
the gallows. And besides when a man is elevated in that odd fashion he has no
proper foundation for his superior altitude. Hence I conclude that in
boasting himself to be high lifted above a whaleman, in that assertion, the
pirate has no solid basis to stand on.
But what is a gam? You might wear out your index finger running up and down
the columns of dictionaries and never find the word. Dr. Johnson never
attained to that erudition. Noah Webster's arc does not hold it.
Nevertheless, this same expressive word has now for many years been in constant
use among some 15,000 trueborn Yankees.
Certainly, it needs a definition and should be incorporated into the lexicon.
With that view, let me learned define it. Gam noun a social meeting of two or
more whale ships generally on a cruising ground when after exchanging hails they
exchange visits by boats crews the two captains remaining for the time on board
of one ship and the two chief mates on the other.
There is another little item about gamming which must not be forgotten
here. All professions have their own little peculiarities of detail. So has
the whale fishery. In a pirate, man of war, or slave ship, when the captain is
rode anywhere in his boat, he always sits in the stern sheets on a
comfortable, sometimes cushioned seat there, and often steers himself with a
pretty little milliner's tiller decorated with gay cords and ribbons.
But the whaleboat has no seat a stern, no sofa of that sort, whatever, and no
tiller at all. High times indeed, if whailing captains were wheeled about the
water on casters like gouty old alderman in patent chairs. And as for the tiller,
the whaleboat never admits of any such effeminacy, and therefore, as in
gamming, a complete boat's crew must leave the ship, and hence, as the boat
steerer or harpooner is of that number, that subordinate is the steersman upon
the occasion, and the captain, having no place to sit in, is pulled off to his
visit, all standing like a pine tree.
And often you will notice that being conscious of the eyes of the whole
visible world resting on him from the sides of the two ships, this standing
captain is all alive to the importance of sustaining his dignity by maintaining
his legs. Nor is this any very easy matter, for in his rear is the immense
projecting steering ore hitting him now and then in the small of his back, the
aftere reciprocating by wrapping his knees in front. He is thus completely
wedged before and behind, and can only expand himself sideways by settling down
on his stretched legs. But a sudden, violent pitch of the boat will often go
far to topple him, because length of foundation is nothing without
corresponding breadth. Merely make a spread angle of two poles, and you
cannot stand them up. Then again, it would never do in plain sight of the
world's riveted eyes. It would never do, I say, for this straddling captain to be
seen steadying himself the slightest particle by catching hold of anything
with his hands. Indeed, as token of his entire buoyant self-comand, he generally
carries his hands in his trousers pockets, but perhaps being generally
very large, heavy hands, he carries them there for ballast. Nevertheless, there
have occurred instances, well authenticated ones too, where the
captain has been known for an uncommonly critical moment or two in a sudden
squall, say, to seize hold of the nearest orarssman's hair and hold on there like grim death.